<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A confutation of atheism from the structure and origin of human bodies. Part I a sermon preached at Saint Martin's in the Fields, May 2. 1692.  Being the third of the lecture founded by the Honourable Robert Boyle, Esquire / by Richard Bentley.</title>
            <author>Bentley, Richard, 1662-1742.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1921A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175533</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64550946</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 64550946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181316</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181316)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2859:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A confutation of atheism from the structure and origin of human bodies. Part I a sermon preached at Saint Martin's in the Fields, May 2. 1692.  Being the third of the lecture founded by the Honourable Robert Boyle, Esquire / by Richard Bentley.</title>
                  <author>Bentley, Richard, 1662-1742.</author>
                  <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
                  <author>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. H. for H. Mortlock at the Phoeniz in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts, XVII, 27 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Christianity and atheism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Atheism --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Atheism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:181316:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181316:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Confutation of Atheiſm From the Structure and Origin of Human Bodies.</p>
            <p>PART I.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Saint</hi> Martin's in the Fields, <hi>May</hi> 2. 1692.</p>
            <p>Being the <hi>Third</hi> of the Lecture Founded by the Honourable <hi>ROBERT BOYLE,</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD BENTLEY,</hi> M. A. Chaplain to the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>EDWARD,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Third Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>H. Mortlock</hi> at the <hi>Phoenix</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:181316:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Geo. Royſe,</hi> R. R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> in Chriſto Patri ac D<hi rend="sup">no</hi> D<hi rend="sup">no</hi> 
                  <hi>Johanni</hi> Archiep <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuar.</hi> à Sacris Domeſt.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 7. 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:181316:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ACTS XVII. 27.</hi> That they ſhould ſeek the Lord, if haply they might feel after him, and find him: though he be not far from every one of us; for in him we Live, and Move, and have our Being.</head>
            <p>I Have ſaid enough in my laſt, to ſhew the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and pertinency of the Apoſtle's Diſcourſe to the Perſons he addreſs'd to: whereby it ſufficiently appears that he was no <hi>Babler,</hi> as ſome of the <hi>Athenian</hi> Rabble reproached him; not a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a buſie prating Fellow; as in another language they ſay <hi>Sermones ſerere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plautus. Virgil. Livius.</note> and <hi>Rumores ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere</hi> in a like mode of Expreſſion; that he did not talk at random, but was throughly acquainted with the ſeveral humors and opinions of his Auditors. And as <hi>Moſes was learned in all the Wiſdom of the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> ſo it is manifeſt from this Chapter alone, if nothing elſe had been now extant, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a great Maſter in all the Learning of the <hi>Greeks.</hi> One thing further I ſhall obſerve from the words of the Text, before I enter upon the Subject which I propoſed; That it requires <hi>ſome</hi> Induſtry and Conſideration to find out the Being of God; we muſt <hi>ſeek the Lord,</hi> and <hi>feel after him,</hi> before we can <hi>find</hi> him by the Light of Nature. The ſearch indeed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:181316:3"/>is not very tedious, nor difficult; <hi>He not far from every one of us; or in him we live, and move, and have our Being.</hi> The Conſideration of our Mind and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which is an incorporeal Subſtance inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent from Matter; and the contemplation of our own Bodies, which have all the ſtamps and characters of excellent Contrivance; theſe alone, though we look upon nothing abroad, do very eaſily and proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately guide us to the wiſe Author of all things. But however, as we ſee from our Text, <hi>ſome</hi> Thoughts and Meditation are neceſſary to it; and a man may poſſibly be ſo ſtupid, or wilfully ignorant or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, as not to have <hi>God in all his thoughts,</hi> or to <hi>ſay in his heart, There is none.</hi> And this being obſerved, we have an effectual anſwer to that Cavil of the Atheiſts; who make it an objection againſt the Being of God, that they do not diſcover him without any Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, in ſpite of their corrupt Wills and debauch'd Underſtandings. If, ſay they, ſuch a God as we are told of, had created and formed us, ſurely he would have left upon our Minds a native and indeleble In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Himſelf, whereby we muſt needs have <hi>felt</hi> him, even without <hi>ſeeking,</hi> and believed in him whether we would or no. So that theſe Atheiſts being conſcious to themſelves, that they are void of ſuch Belief, which (they ſay) if God was, would actually and neceſſarily be in them, do bring their own wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:181316:3"/>Doubting and Denying of God, as Evidence againſt His Exiſtence, and make their very Infidelity an argument for it ſelf. To which we reply, That God hath endu'd Mankind with Powers and Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which we call Natural Light, and Reaſon, and Common Senſe; by the due uſe of which we cannot miſs of the Diſcovery of his Being; and this is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. But as to any other original Notion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that <hi>God is,</hi> actually imprinted on us, ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently to all uſe of our Faculties, we may affirm againſt the Atheiſts, that the abſence of ſuch a Notion doth not give the leaſt preſumption againſt the truth of Religion; becauſe, though God be ſuppos'd to be, yet that Notion diſtinct from our Faculties would not be requiſite; nor is it pretended to by Religion. <hi>Firſt,</hi> it would not be requiſite; becauſe, without any ſuch primitive Impreſſion, we can eaſily attain to the knowledge of the Deity by the ſole uſe of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon. And again, ſuch an Impreſſion would have render'd the Belief of a God irreſiſtible and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and thereby have bereaved it of all that is good and acceptable in it. For as by taking away the Freedom of Human Will, and making us meer Machins under fatal Ties and Impulſes, it would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the very nature of Moral Vertue; ſo likewiſe as to Faith, there would be nothing worthy of praiſe and recompence in it, if there were left no poſſibility
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:181316:4"/>of Doubting or Denying. And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> ſuch a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Truth, that <hi>God is,</hi> ſpringing up together with the Eſſence of the Soul, and previous to all other Thoughts, is not pretended to by Religion. No ſuch thing, that I know of, is affirmed or ſuggeſted by the Scriptures. There are ſeveral Topics there uſed againſt the Atheiſm and Idolatry of the Heathens; ſuch as the viſible marks of Divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs in the Works of the Creation, the vital U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Souls with Matter, and the admirable Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of animate Bodies, and the like. But if our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle had aſſerted ſuch an anticipating Principle engraven upon our Souls before all Exerciſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; what did he talk of <hi>ſeeking the Lord, if haply they might feel after him and find him:</hi> ſeeing that if the knowledge of him was in that manner innate and perpetual, there would be no occaſion of <hi>ſeeking,</hi> nor any <hi>hap</hi> or hazard in the finding. Such an Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would be ſelf-evident without any Ratiocinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Study, and could not fail conſtantly to exert its Energy in their Minds. What did he talk of the <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known God,</hi> and <hi>ignorantly worſhipping;</hi> when if ſuch an Original Signature were always inherent in their hearts; God could not be unknown to, or ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhipp'd by any? That primary Propoſition would have been clear, and diſtinct, and efficacious, and univerſal in the minds of Men. S. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:181316:4"/>it appears, had no apprehenſion of ſuch a Firſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; nor made uſe of it for an argument; which (ſeeing that whoſoever hath it, muſt needs know that he hath it) if it be not believed before by the Adverſary, is falſe; and if it be believed, is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous; and is of ſo frail and brittle a texture, that whereas other arguments are not anſwered by bare denying without contrary Proof, the meer doubting and disbelieving of this muſt be granted to be <hi>ipſo facto</hi> the breaking and confuting of it. Thus much therefore we have proved againſt the Atheiſt; that ſuch an original irreſiſtible Notion is neither requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite upon, ſuppoſition of a Deity, nor is pretended to by Religion; ſo that neither the Abſence of it is any Argument againſt the Being of God, nor a ſuppoſed falſe Aſſertion of it an objection againſt the Scripture. 'Tis enough that all are furniſh'd with ſuch Natural Powers and Capacities; that if they ſeriouſly reflect, if they <hi>ſeek the Lord</hi> with meditation and ſtudy, they cannot fail of <hi>finding</hi> and diſcovering him: whereby God is not <hi>left without witneſs,</hi> but the Atheiſt <hi>without excuſe.</hi> And now I haſte to the Second Propoſition deduced from the Text, and the Argument of my preſent Diſcourſe, That the organical Structure of humane Bodies, whereby they are fitted to live, and move, and be vitally informed by the Soul, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably the workmanſhip of a moſt wiſe, and powerfull, and beneficent Maker.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:181316:5"/>
            <p> Firſt, 'Tis allowed and acknowledged by all parties, that the Bodies of Men and other Animals are excellently well fitted for Life, and Motion, and Senſation; and the ſeveral Parts of them well adapted and accommodated to their particular Functions. The Eye is very proper and meet for ſeeing, the Tongue for taſting and ſpeaking, the Hand for holding and lifting, and ten thouſand Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations beſide: and ſo for the inward Parts; the Lungs are ſuitable for Reſpiration, the Stomach for Concoction, the Lacteous Veſſels for the Reception of the Chyle, the Heart for the Diſtribution of the Blood to all the parts of the Body. This is matter of Fact, and beyond all diſpute; and in effect is no more than to ſay, that <hi>Animals are Animals;</hi> for if they were depriv'd of theſe Qualifications, they could not be ſo. This therefore is not the matter in Queſtion between us and the Atheiſts: But the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie is here. We, when we conſider ſo many conſtituent parts in the Bodies of Men, all admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly compacted into ſo noble an Engine; in each of the very Fingers, for example, there are Bones, and Griſtles, and Ligaments, and Membranes, and Muſcles, and Tendons, and Nerves, and Arteries, and Veins, and Skin, and Cuticle, and Nail; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Marrow, and Fat, and Blood, and other Nutritious Juices; and all thoſe ſolid Parts of a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:181316:5"/>determinate Size, and Figure, and Texture, and Situ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; and each of them made up of Myriads of little Fibres and Filaments, not diſcoverable by the naked Eye: I ſay, when we conſider how innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parts muſt conſtitute ſo ſmall a member, as the Finger, we cannot look upon <hi>it</hi> or the whole Body, wherein appears ſo much Fitneſs and Uſe, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviency to infinite Functions, any otherwiſe than as the effect of Contrivance and Skill, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Workmanſhip of a moſt Intelligent and Beneficent Being. And though now the Propagation of Mankind is in a ſettled method of Nature, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of God: yet we affirm that its firſt Produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was by the immediate Power of the Almighty Author of Nature: and that all ſucceeding Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men are the Progeny of one primitive Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. This is a Religious Man's account of the Frame and Origination of himſelf. Now the Atheiſts agree with us, as to the Fitneſs of Man's Body and its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Parts to their various Operations and Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (for that is viſible and paſt all contradiction) but they vehemently impugn, and horribly dread the Thought, That this Uſefulneſs of the Parts and the Whole ſhould firſt ariſe from Wiſdom and Deſign. So that here will be the point in debate, and the ſubject of our preſent Undertaking; Whether this acknowledged Fitneſs of Human Bodies muſt be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:181316:6"/>attributed, as we ſay, to a wiſe and good God; or, as the Atheiſts averr, to dead, ſenſleſs Matter. They have contrived ſeveral tricks and <hi>methods of Deceit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eph. 4.14.</note> one repugnant to another, to evade (if poſſible) this moſt cogent Proof of a Deity; All which I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and refute: and I hope to make it appear, that here, as indeed every where, but here certainly, in the great Dramatick Poem of Nature, is <hi>dignus Deo vindice Nodus,</hi> a neceſſity of introducing a God.</p>
            <p>And firſt, I will anſwer what Exceptions they can have againſt Our account: and ſecondly, I will confute all the Reaſons and Explications they can give of their Own.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> I will anſwer what Exceptions they can have againſt Our account of the Production of Mankind. And they may object, That the Body it ſelf, though pretty good in its Kind and upon Their <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> nevertheleſs doth not look like the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of ſo great a Maſter, as is pretended by Us; that infinite Wiſdom, and Goodneſs, and Power, would have beſtowed upon us more Senſes than five, or at leaſt theſe five in a much higher Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; that we could never have come out of the Hands of the Almighty, ſo ſubject to numerous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, ſo obnoxious to violent Deaths; and, at beſt, of ſuch a ſhort and tranſitory Life. They can no more aſcribe ſo ſorry an Effect to an Omniſcient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:181316:6"/>Cauſe, than ſome ordinary piece of Clock-work with a very few motions and uſes, and thoſe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually out of order, and quickly at an end, to the beſt Artiſt of the Age. But to this we reply: <hi>Firſt,</hi> as to the five Senſes, it would be raſh indeed to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That God, though he had pleaſed, could not have endued us with more. But thus much we may averr, That though the Power of God be infinite and perfect, yet the Capacities of Matter are within limits and bounds. Why then doth the Atheiſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that there may poſſibly be any more ways of Senſation than what we have already? Hath he an Idea, or Notion, or Diſcovery of any more? So far from that, that he cannot make any addition or progreſs in thoſe very Senſes he hath, further than they themſelves have informed him. He cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine one new Colour, or Taſte, or Smell, beſide thoſe that have actually fallen under his reſpective Senſes. Much leſs can he that is deſtitute of an entire Senſe, have any Idea or Repreſentation of it; as one that is born Deaf hath no Notion of Sounds; or Blind, of Colours and Light. If then the Atheiſt can have no Imagination of more Senſes than five, why doth he ſuppoſe that a Body is capable of more? If we had double or triple as many, there might ſtill be the ſame ſuſpicion for a greater number without end; and therefore in both caſes 'tis equally unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:181316:7"/>and groundleſs. <hi>Secondly,</hi> we affirm, that our Senſes have that degree of Perfection which is moſt fit and ſuitable to our Eſtate and Condition. If the <hi>Eye</hi> were ſo piercing, as to deſcry even opake and little Objects a hundred Leagues off, it would do us little ſervice; it would be terminated by neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Hills and Woods, or in the largeſt and eveneſt plain by the very Convexity of the Earth, unleſs we could always inhabit the tops of Mountains and Cliffs, or had Wings too to fly aloft, when we had a mind to take a Proſpect. And if mankind had had Wings (as perhaps ſome extravagant Atheiſt may think us deficient in that) all the World muſt have conſented to clip them; or elſe Human Race had been extinct before this time, nothing upon that ſuppoſition being ſafe from Murder and Rapine. Or if the <hi>Eye</hi> were ſo acute, as to rival the fineſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſcopes, and to diſcern the ſmalleſt Hair upon the leg of a Gnat, it would be a curſe and not a bleſſing to us; it would make all things appear rugged and deformed; the moſt finely poliſh'd Chryſtal would be uneven and rough: The ſight of our own ſelves would affright us: The ſmootheſt Skin would be beſet all over with ragged Scales, and briſtly Hairs. And beſide, we could not ſee at one view above what is now the ſpace of an Inch, and it would take a conſiderable time to ſurvey the then mountainous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:181316:7"/>bulk of our own Bodies. Such a Faculty of ſight ſo diſproportion'd to our other Senſes and to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects about us would be very little better than Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ſelf. And again, God hath furniſhed us with Invention and Induſtry, ſo that by optical Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes we can more than ſupply that imaginary defect of our own Eyes, and diſcover more remote and minute Bodies with that aſſiſtance than perhaps the moſt whimſical Atheiſt would deſire to do without it. So likewiſe if our Sence of <hi>Hearing</hi> were exalted proportionably to the former, what a miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition would Mankind be in? What whiſper could be low enough, but many would over-hear it? What Affairs, that moſt require it, could be tranſacted with ſecrecy? and whither could we retire from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual humming and buzzing? every breath of Wind would incommode and diſturb us: we ſhould have no quiet or ſleep in the ſilenteſt nights and moſt ſolitary places; and we muſt inevitably be ſtricken Deaf or Dead with the noiſe of a clap of Thunder. And the like inconveniences would follow, if the Senſe of <hi>Feeling</hi> was advanced to ſuch a degree, as the Atheiſt requires. How could we ſuſtain the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our very Cloaths in ſuch a condition; much leſs carry burthens and provide for conveniences of Life? We could not bear the aſſault of an Inſect, or a Feather, or a puff of Air without pain. There
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:181316:8"/>are examples now of wounded perſons, that have roared for anguiſh and torment at the diſcharge of Ordnance, though at a very great diſtance; what inſupportable torture then ſhould we be under upon a like concuſſion in the Air, when all the whole Body would have the tenderneſs of a Wound? In a word, all the Changes and Emendations that the Atheiſts would make in our Senſes, are ſo far from being Improvements, that they would prove the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ruin and Extirpation of Mankind.</p>
            <p>But perhaps they may have better ſucceſs in their complaints about the Diſtempers of the Body and the Shortneſs of Life. We do not wonder indeed, that the Atheiſt ſhould lay a mighty ſtreſs upon this Objection. For to a man that places all his Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in the Indolency and Pleaſure of the Body, what can be more terrible than Pain or a Fit of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs nothing but <hi>Death</hi> alone, the moſt dreadfull thing in the world. When an Atheiſt reflects upon Death, his very Hope is Deſpair; and 'tis the crown and top of his Wiſhes, that it may prove his utter Diſſolution and Deſtruction. No queſtion if an Atheiſt had had the making of himſelf, he would have framed a Conſtitution that could have kept pace with his inſatiable Luſt, been invincible by Gluttony and Intemperance, and have held out vigorous a thouſand years in a perpetual Debauch.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:181316:8"/>But we anſwer; <hi>Firſt,</hi> in the words of St. <hi>Paul: Nay but, O Man, who art thou,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.20.</note> 
               <hi>that replieſt againſt God? ſhall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it, Why haſt thou made me thus?</hi> We adore and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his moſt holy Name for his undeſerved Mercy towards us, that he made us the Chief of the viſible Creation; and freely acquit his Goodneſs from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny imputation of Unkindneſs, that he has placed us no Higher. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Religion gives us a very good account of the preſent Infirmity of our Bodies. Man at his firſt Origin was a Veſſel of Honour, when he came firſt out of the Hands of the Potter: endued with all imaginable Perfections of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Nature; till by Diſobedience and Sin, Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Death came firſt into the World. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Diſtempers of the Body are not ſo formidable to a Religious Man, as they are to an Atheiſt: He hath a quite different judgment and apprehenſion about them: he is willing to believe, that our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition is better for us in the Iſſue, than that uninterrupted Health and Security, that the Atheiſt deſires; which would ſtrongly tempt us to forget God and the concerns of a better Life. Whereas now he receives a Fit of Sickneſs, as the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the kind Chaſtiſement and Diſcipline of his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, to wean his Affections from the World, where he is but as on a Journey; and to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:181316:9"/>fix his thoughts and deſires on things above, where his Country and his Dwelling is: that where he hath placed his <hi>Treaſure</hi> and Concerns, <hi>there his heart may be alſo. Fourthly,</hi> Moſt of the Diſtempers that are incident to us are of our own making, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of abuſed Plenty, and Luxury, and muſt not be charged upon our Maker; who notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Riches of his Compaſſion hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for us ſtore of excellent Medicines, to allevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in a great meaſure thoſe very Evils which we bring upon our ſelves. And now we are come to the laſt objection of the Atheiſt, That Life is too ſhort. Alas for him, what pity 'tis that he cannot wallow immortally in his ſenſual Pleaſures! If his Life were many whole Ages longer than it is, he would ſtill make the ſame Complaint, <hi>Brevis eſt hic fructus homullis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lucret. <hi>l.</hi> 3.</note> For Eternity, and that's the thing he trembles at, is every whit as long after a thouſand years as after fifty. But Religion gives us a better proſpect and makes us look beyond the gloomy Regions of Death with Comfort and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: <hi>When this corruptible ſhall put on incorruption, and this mortal put on immortality.</hi> We are ſo far from repining at God, that he hath not extended the period of our Lives to the Longaevity of the Antediluvians; that we give him thanks for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting the Days of our Trial, and receiving us
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:181316:9"/>more maturely into thoſe Everlaſting Habitations above, that he hath prepared for us.</p>
            <p>And now that I have anſwer'd all the Atheiſt's Exceptions againſt Our account of the Production of Mankind, I come in the next place to examine all the Reaſons and Explications they can give of their own.</p>
            <p>The Atheiſts upon this occaſion are divided into Sects, and (which is the mark and character of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror) are at variance and repugnancy with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and with themſelves. <hi>Some</hi> of them will have Mankind to have been thus from all Eternity. But the reſt do no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> approve of any infinite Succeſſions, but are poſitive for a beginning; and they alſo are ſubdivided into three Parties: the <hi>firſt</hi> aſcribe the Origin of Men to the Influence of the Stars upon ſome extraordinary Conjunction or Aſpect: Others again reject all Aſtrology; and <hi>ſome</hi> of theſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanically produce Mankind at the very firſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment by the action of the Sun upon duly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Matter: but <hi>others</hi> are rather of opinion, that after infinite blundering and miſcarrying our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies at laſt happen'd and jump'd into this Figure by meer Chance and Accident. There's no Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt in the World, that reaſons about his Infidelity (which God knows moſt of them never do) but he takes one of theſe <hi>four</hi> Methods. I will refute
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181316:10"/>them every one in the ſame order that I have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them: the two former in the preſent Diſcourſe, reſerving the others for another occaſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Opinion of thoſe Atheiſts that will have Mankind and other Animals to have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted thus eternally in infinite Generations already paſt, will be found to be flat Nonſence and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to it ſelf, and repugnant alſo to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact. <hi>Firſt,</hi> it is contradiction to its ſelf. Infinite Generations of Men (they ſay) are already paſt and gone: but whatſoever is now paſt, was once actually preſent; ſo that each of thoſe Infinite Generations was once in its turn actually preſent: therefore all except One Generation were once fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and not in being, which deſtroys the very ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: For either that One Generation muſt it ſelf have been Infinite, which is Nonſence; or it was the Finite Beginning of Infinite Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons between it ſelf and us, which is Infinity ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated at both ends, which is nonſence as before. <hi>Again,</hi> Infinite paſt Generations of Men have been once actually preſent: therefore there may be ſome one Man of them given, that was at infinite diſtance from <hi>us</hi> now: therefore that man's Son likewiſe, ſuppoſe forty years younger than his Father, was either at infinite diſtance from us or at finite: if that Son too was at infinite diſtance from us, then one
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:181316:10"/>Infinite is longer by forty years than another; which is abſurd: if at finite, then forty years added to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite makes it infinite, which is as abſurd as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And <hi>again,</hi> The number of Men that are already dead and gone is infinite, as they ſay: but the number of the Eyes of thoſe men muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be twice as much as that of the men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that of the Fingers ten times as much, and that of the Hairs of their Heads thouſands of times. So that we have here one Infinite number twice, ten times, and thouſands of times as great as another, which is contradiction again. Thus we ſee it is impoſſible in it ſelf, that any ſucceſſive duration ſhould be actually and poſitively infinite, or have infinite ſucceſſions already gone and paſt. Neither can theſe Difficulties be applied to the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Duration of God Almighty. For thou we cannot comprehend Eternity and Infinity; yet we underſtand what they are <hi>not.</hi> And ſomething, we are ſure, muſt have Exiſted from all Eternity; becauſe all things could not emerge and ſtart out of Nothing. So that if this prae-exiſtent Eternity is not compatible with a ſucceſſive Duration, as we clearly and diſtinctly perceive that it is not; then it remains, that ſome Being, though infinitely above our finite comprehenſions, muſt have had an iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, invariable Continuance from all Eternity;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:181316:11"/>which Being is no other than God. For as his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is perfect and immutable without the <hi>leaſt ſhadow of change;</hi> ſo his Eternal Duration is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent and indiviſible, not meaſurable by Time and Motion, nor to be computed by number of ſucceſſive Moments. <hi>One day with the Lord is as a thouſand years, and a thouſand years as one day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> this Opinion of infinite Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is repugnant likewiſe to matter of Fact. Tis a Truth beyond oppoſition, that the univerſal Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Mankind hath had a gradual increaſe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding what War, and Famine, and Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and Floods, and Conflagrations, and the Religious Profeſſion of Celibracy, and other Cauſes, may at certain periods of time have interrupted and retarded it. This is manifeſt from the Hiſtory of the Jewiſh Nation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon the Bills of Mortality.</note> from the account of the Roman <hi>Cenſus,</hi> and Regiſters of our Own Country, where the proportion of Births to Burials is found upon obſervation to be yearly as Fifty to Forty. Now if Mankind do increaſe, though never ſo ſlowly, but one Couple ſuppoſe in an Age; 'tis enough to evince the falſhood of Infinite Generations already expired. For though an Atheiſt ſhould contend, that there were ten thouſand million couple of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind now in being, (that we may allow him mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude enough) 'tis but going back ſo many Ages,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:181316:11"/>and we deſcend to a ſingle Original Pair. And 'tis all one in reſpect of Eternal Duration yet behind, whether we begin the world ſo many millions of Ages ago, or date it from the late <hi>Aera</hi> of about Six Thouſand years. And moreover this recent beginning of the World is further eſtabliſhed from the known Original of Empires and Kingdoms, and the Invention of Arts and Sciences: whereas if infinite Ages of Mankind had already preceded, there could nothing have been left to be invented or improved by the ſucceſsfull induſtry and curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of our own. The Circulation of the Blood, and the Weight and Spring of the Air (which is as it were the Vital Pulſe and the great Circulation of Nature, and of more importance in all Phyſiology, than any one Invention ſince the beginning of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) had never lain hidden ſo many myriads of Generations, and been reſerved for a late happy Diſcovery by two great Luminaries of this Iſland. I know the Atheiſt may endeavour to evade this by ſuppoſing, That though Mankind have been from everlaſting, and have perpetually encreas'd by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; yet at certain great periods there may be univerſal Deluges, which may <hi>not</hi> wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh Mankind (for, they'll ſay, there is not Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enough in Nature for that) but may cover the Earth to ſuch a Height, that none but a few Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181316:12"/>may eſcape, enough to continue Humane Race; and yet being illiterate Ruſticks (as Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers always are) they can preſerve no Memoirs of former times, nor propagate any Sciences or Arts; and ſo the world muſt needs be thought by Poſterity to have begun at ſuch periods. But to this I anſwer, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That upon this ſuppoſition there muſt have been infinite Deluges already paſt: for if ever this Atheiſt admits of a firſt Deluge, he is in the ſame nooſe that he was. For then he muſt aſſert, That there were infinite generations and an infinite increaſe of mankind before that firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge; and then the Earth could not receive them, but the infinite Bodies of Men muſt occupy an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Space, and then all the Matter of the Univerſe muſt be humane Body, and other abſurdities that follow it, which are infinite too. But if he ſays, That there have been infinite Deluges heretofore, this is impoſſibility again; for all that I ſaid before againſt the Notion of infinite paſt Generations, is alike applicable to this. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Such Univerſal Deluges (ſeeing the Deity is now excluded) muſt be produced in a natural way: and therefore gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually, and not in an inſtant: and therefore (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the tops of Mountains, they ſay, are never overflown) the civilized people may eſcape thither out of Villages and Cities; and conſequently, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:181316:12"/>the Atheiſt, Arts, and Sciences, and Hiſtories, may be preſerved, and derived to the ſucceeding World. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let us imagin the whole Terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queous Globe with its Atmoſphere about it; What is there here, that can naturally effect an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Deluge? If you would drown one Country or Continent with Rains and Inundations, you muſt borrow your Vapor and Water from ſome other part of the Globe. You can never overflow all at a time. If the Atmoſphere it ſelf was reduced into Water, (as ſome think it poſſible) it would not make an O<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b above 32 foot deep, which would ſoon be ſwallowed up by the cavity of the Sea, and the depreſſed parts of the Earth, and be a very feeble attempt towards an Univerſal Deluge. But then what immenſe Weight is there above, that muſt overcome the expanſive force of the Air, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it into near the thouſandth part of the room that it now takes up? <hi>We,</hi> that acknowledge a God Almighty, can give an account of one Deluge, by ſaying it was miraculous; but it would be a little ſtrange to ſee an Atheiſt have recourſe to a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle; and that not once only, but upon infinite oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. But perhaps they may endeavour to prove the poſſibility of ſuch a natural Deluge, by bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing an ingenious Notion, and pretending, That the face of Nature may be now quite changed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:181316:13"/>from what it was; and that formerly the whole Collection of Waters might be an orbicular Abyſs, arched over with an exterior Cruſt or Shell of Earth; and that the breaking and fall of this Cruſt might naturally make a Deluge. I'll allow the Atheiſt all the fair play in the world. Let us ſuppoſe the Fall of this imaginary Cruſt. <hi>Firſt,</hi> It ſeems to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, but that all the Inhabitants of this Cruſt muſt be daſh'd to pieces in its Ruins. So that this very Notion brings us to the neceſſity of a new pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of Men; to evade which it is introduced by the Atheiſt. <hi>Again,</hi> If ſuch a Cruſt naturally fell, then it had in its own conſtitution a tendency towards a Fall; that is, it was more likely and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to fall this thouſand years, ſuppoſe, than the laſt. But if the Cruſt was always gradually nearer and nearer to falling; that plainly evinces, that it had not endured eternally before its Fall. For let them aſſign any imaginable period for its falling, how could it have held out till then (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſuppoſition) the unmeaſurable du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of infinite Ages before? And <hi>again,</hi> ſuch a Cruſt could fall but once; for what Architect can an Atheiſt ſuppoſe, to rebuild a new Arch out of the ruins of the other? But I have ſhewn before, that this Atheiſt hath need of infinite Deluges to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his deſign; and therefore I'll leave him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:181316:13"/>how to make infinite Cruſts one upon the back of another; and now proceed to examine in the ſecond place, The Aſtrological Explication of the Origin of Men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you ask one of this Party, what Evidence he is able to produce for the truth of his Art, he may perhaps offer ſome Phyſical Reaſons for a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral influence of the Stars upon terreſtrial bodies: but as Aſtrology is conſider'd as a Syſtem of Rules and Propoſitions, he will not pretend to give any reaſon of it <hi>à priori;</hi> but reſolves all that into Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> who firſt learnt it by long obſervation, and tranſmitted it down to Poſterity; and that now it is daily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Events, which are experienced to anſwer the Predictions. This is all that can be ſaid for Aſtrology as an Art. So that the whole Credibility of this Planetary production of Mankind muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon Obſervation. But are they able to ſhew among all the Remains of the <hi>Chaldaick</hi> Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Four hundred and ſeventy thouſand years (as they pretended) any Tradition of ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction? So far from that, that the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the world and mankind to have been from everlaſting, which opinion I have refuted before. Neither can the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Wizards with their long Catalogue of Dynaſties, and Obſervations for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Years, ſupply the Atheiſts with one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:181316:14"/>of ſuch a Creation. Where are the fragments of <hi>Petoſiris</hi> and <hi>Necepſo,</hi> that may countenance this Aſſertion? I believe if they had had any example of men born out of the Soil, they would rather have aſcribed it to the fruitfull Mud of the <hi>Nile</hi> (as they did the breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Frogs,<note place="margin">So <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi> lib. 1. c. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> and Mice, and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) than to the efficacy of Stars. But with the leave of theſe Fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellers did the Stars do this feat once only, which gave beginning to Human Race? or have they frequently done ſo, and may do it again? If fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, why is not this Rule deliver'd in <hi>Ptolemy</hi> and <hi>Albumaſar?</hi> If once only at the beginning, then how came it to be diſcover'd? Who were there then in the world, to obſerve the Births of thoſe Firſt Men, and calculate their Nativities, as they ſprawl'd out of Ditches? Thoſe Sons of Earth were very wiſe Children if they themſelves knew, that the Stars were their Fathers. Unleſs we are to imagine, that they underſtood the Planets and the Zodiack by inſtinct, and fell to drawing Schemes of their own Horoſcopes, in the ſame Duſt they ſprung out of? For my part I can have no great veneration for <hi>Chalda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick</hi> Antiquity;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vitruvius,</hi> lib. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>4. Lucret.</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Babylonica Chaldaeum doctrina, &amp;c. <hi>Apuleius</hi> de Deo <hi>Socratis:</hi> Seu illa (Luna) proprio &amp; perpeti fulgore, ut <hi>Chaldaei</hi> arbitrantur, parte luminis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos, parte altera caſſa fulgoris.</note> when I ſee they could not diſcover in ſo many thouſand years, that the Moon was an opake
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:181316:14"/>Body, and received her Light from the Sun. But ſuppoſe their Obſervations had been never ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate, it could add no Authority to modern Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, which is borrowed from the <hi>Greeks.</hi> 'Tis well known that <hi>Beroſus,</hi> or his Scholars, new mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled and adapted the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Doctrines to the <hi>Grecian</hi> Mythology. The ſuppoſed Influences of <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Taurus</hi> for example, have a manifeſt rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Grecian</hi> Stories of the Ram that carried <hi>Phrixus,</hi> and the Bull that carried <hi>Europa.</hi> Now which of theſe is the Copy, and which the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal? Were the Fables taken from the Influences, or the Influences from the Fables? the Poetical Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, more ancient than all Records of Hiſtory; or the Aſtrological Influences, that were not known to the <hi>Greeks</hi> till after <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great? But without queſtion thoſe Fabulous Tales had been many a time told and ſung to lull children aſleep, before ever <hi>Beroſus</hi> ſet up his Intelligence-Office at <hi>Coos.</hi> And the ſame may be ſaid of all the other Conſtellations. Firſt, Poetry had filled the Skies with Aſteriſms and Hiſtories belong to them; and then Aſtrology deviſes the feigned Virtues and Influences of each, from ſome property of the Image, or alluſion to the Story. And the ſame tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling futility appears in their XII Signs of the <hi>Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack,</hi> and their mutual Relations and Aſpects. Why no more Aſpects than diametrically oppoſite, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:181316:15"/>ſuch as make aequlateral figures? Why are the Maſculine and Feminine, the Fiery and Airy, and Watry and Earthly Signs all placed at ſuch regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar diſtances? Were the Virtues of the Stars diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in that order and rank, on purpoſe only to make a pretty Diagram upon Paper? But the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical Aſtrologer is doubly preſſed with this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity. For if there was no Counſel at the making of the world, how came the Aſteriſms of the ſame nature and energies to be ſo harmoniouſly placed at regular intervals? And how could all the Stars of one Aſteriſm agree and conſpire together to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute an Univerſal? Why does not every ſingle Star ſhed a ſeparate influence; and have Aſpects with other Stars of their own Conſtellation? But what need there many words? As if the late Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of the Celeſtial Bodies had not plainly detected the impoſture of Aſtrology? The Planet <hi>Saturn</hi> is found to have a great Ring that encircles him, and three leſſer Planets that move about him, as the Moon doth about the Earth: and <hi>Jupiter</hi> hath four <hi>Satellites,</hi> which by their Interpoſition between him and us make ſome hundreds of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſes every year. Now the whole Tribe of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers, that never dream'd of theſe Planets have always declared, that when <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> come about again to any given Point, they exert (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd ſingly by themſelves) the ſame Influence
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:181316:15"/>as before. But 'tis now manifeſt, that when either of them return to the ſame point; the Planets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, that muſt make up an united Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with them, have a different ſituation in reſpect of us and each other, from what they had the time before: and conſequently the joint Influence muſt be perpetually varied, and never be reducible to any Rules and Obſervations. Or if the Influences be conveyed hither diſtinct, yet ſometimes ſome of the Little Planets will eclipſe the Great one at any given point; and therefore intercept and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Influence. I cannot now inſiſt on many other Arguments deducible from the late Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Aſtronomy; For if the Earth be not the Centre of the Planetary Motions, what muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come then of the preſent Aſtrology, which is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adapted to that vulgar <hi>Hypotheſis?</hi> And yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, when they lay under ſuch wretched mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes for many Myriads of Years, if we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to believe them; they would all along, as now, appeal to Experience and Event for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of their Doctrins. That's the invincible Demonſtration ſo the Verity of the Science: And indeed as to their Predictions, I think our Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers may aſſume to themſelves that infallible Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of <hi>Tireſias,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>O Laertiade, quicquid dico, aut erit, aut non.</q>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:181316:16"/>
            <p> There's but a true and a falſe in any telling of Fortune; and a man that never hits on the right ſide, cannot be called a bad Gueſſer, but muſt miſs out of deſign, and be notably skilfull at light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the wrong. And were there not formerly as great pretenſions to it from the ſuperſtitious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Entrails of Cows, of the flying of Vulturs, and the pecking of Chickens? Nay, the old <hi>Augurs</hi> and <hi>Southſayers</hi> had better reaſon to profeſs the Art of Divining, than the modern Aſtrological Atheiſt: for They ſuppoſed there were ſome <hi>Daemons,</hi> that directed the Indications. So likewiſe the <hi>Chaldean</hi> and <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Aſtrologers were much more excuſable than He. It was the Religion of their Countries to worſhip the Stars, as we know from unqueſtionable Authority. They believed them Ingelligent Beings, and no other than very Gods;<note place="margin">Maimonides More Nevochim <hi>De Zabiis &amp; Chaldaeis.</hi> Plato <hi>in</hi> Cratylo. Diodorus, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. Euſebius <hi>Demonſt. Evangel. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and therefore had ſome Reaſon to ſuſpect, that they might govern Human Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. The Influence of the Stars was in their apprehenſions no leſs than Divine Power. But an Atheiſt, that believes the Planets to be dark, ſolid and ſenſleſs Bodies, like the brute Earth he treads on; and the Fixt Stars and the Sun to be inanimate Balls of Fire; what Reaſons can He advance for the credit of ſuch Influences? He acknowledgeth nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:181316:16"/>Matter and Motion; ſo that all that he can conceive to be tranſmitted hither from the Stars, muſt needs be perform'd either by Mechaniſm or Accident: either of which is wholly unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and the latter irreconcilable to any Art or Syſtem of Science. But if both were allowed the Atheiſt; yet as to any production of Mankind, they will be again refuted in my following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. I can preſerve a due eſteem for ſome great Men of the laſt Age, before the Mechanical Philoſophy was revived, though they were too much addicted to this nugatory Art. When Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult Quality, and Sympathy and Antipathy were admitted for ſatisfactory Explications of things, even wiſe and vertuous Men might ſwallow down any Opinion that was countenanced by Antiquity. But at this time of day, when all the general powers and capacities of Matter are ſo clearly underſtood; he muſt be very ridiculous himſelf, that doth not deride and explode the antiquated Folly. But we may ſee the miſerable Shifts that ſome men are put to; when that which was firſt founded upon, and afterward ſupported by <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> is now become the tottering Sanctuary of <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> If the Stars be no Deities, Aſtrology is groundleſs: and if the Stars be Deities, why is the Aſtrologer an Atheiſt? He may eaſily be no Chriſtian; and 'tis difficult indeed to be both at
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:181316:17"/>once: becauſe, as I have ſaid before, Idolatry is at the bottom; and by ſubmitting Human Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Inclinations to the Influence of the Stars, they deſtroy the very Eſſence of Moral Vertue and the Efficacy of Divine Grace:<note place="margin">Concil. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. <hi>Can.</hi> 36. Conc. 6. in Trullo. <hi>Can.</hi> 61. Cod. Juſt. <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>tit.</hi> 18. Cod. Theodoſ. <hi>l</hi> 9. <hi>tit.</hi> 16. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 60. <hi>tit.</hi> 39.</note> and therefore Aſtrology was juſtly condemn'd by the Ancient Fathers and Chriſtian Emperours. An Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I ſay, may very eaſily be no Chriſtian; he may be an Idolater or a Pagan: but I could hardly think Aſtrology to be compatible with rank Atheiſm; if I could ſuppoſe any great gifts of Nature to be, where either do reſide. But let him be what he will, he is not able to do much hurt by his Reaſons and Example. For Religion it ſelf, according to his Principles, is derived from the Stars. And he owns, 'tis not any juſt Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he hath taken againſt Chriſtianity, but 'tis his Deſtiny and Fate; 'tis <hi>Saturn</hi> in the Ninth Houſe, and not Judgment and Deliberation, that made him an Atheiſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:181316:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
